this program is brought to you by
stanford university
i want to come tonight to
the idea of inflation inflation is an
important idea in cosmology
maybe
one of the most important
and uh
sort of at the root of much that we
know much that we suspect about
cosmology
but before i do let me remind you
about what the presence of a
cosmological constant does
in einstein's equations the cosmological
constant i'll remind you is just a term
in the energy
which
doesn't dilute as the universe expands
an energy density which does not dilute
so it's just a term
in einstein's equations einstein's
equations are the same as the friedman
robertson walker maker equations
a dot
over a
squared
is equal
to the energy density
and i'm going to take the case of flat
space although we may want to modify
that later the case in which space
itself is flat not space time but space
and in that case what goes here is just
eight pi over three times newton's
constant times the energy density
and in general the energy density may
dilute
the energy density or mass density
we discussed various cases there was the
case of
matter dominated
where
rho
was just the mass energy of a collection
of particles that are expanding because
it's expanding the energy density
decreases
and in that case rho goes like 1 over a
cubed
we studied the case where rho was
radiation energy that's what dominates
in the very early universe it was 1 over
8 to the 4th
and we also talked about vacuum energy
and vacuum energy
rho is just constant
so we can just call that rho naught or
we can call the whole thing on the right
hand side uh
lambda or something proportional to
lambda there's some
definition of lambda the cosmological
constant
which includes i forget how many eights
and pies and so forth but
this whole right hand side
would be a constant then
all right let's suppose this is a
constant let's call this constant let's
just give it a name
h
squared why am i and h is a constant it
does not change with time
that's
the nature of vacuum energy the nature
of vacuum energy is the right hand side
doesn't change of course the re the
reason i'm calling it h squared instead
of just h is because the left hand side
is a square
and this will uh have the nice
properties when i take the square root
it will say that a dot over a is just
equal to the constant h where h is the
square root of the vacuum energy times g
times 8 pi over 3. that's
that's
square root of
8 pi
g over three times the vacuum energy rho
naught rho naught just means vacuum
energy so if you know the vacuum energy
then you know h as i emphasize
uh
h is a
constant right and then a dot over a is
just equal to that constant this is a
special cosmology that has nothing in it
but vacuum energy
now remember also that a dot over a is
also the hubble constant
so for this very special case where
there is nothing but vacuum energy
nothing but vacuum energy
that is a special case
uh when there's nothing but vacuum
energy the hubble constant is truly
constant it doesn't change with time
if the hubble constant doesn't change
with time
what does that say about a well we can
write it as
a dot which is the a by dt
is equal to this constant hubble
constant times a
and the solution to that equation is an
exponential the rate of change of the
scale factor is proportional to the
scale factor
with a constant of proportionality just
equal to h
and the solution to this is a
is equal to some constant it doesn't
matter we can just ignore what the
constant is and write e to the
ht in other words the scale factor
or the distance between distant galaxies
unbound galaxies galaxies which don't
have enough gravity to
between them to keep them from receding
the distance grows exponentially
that space time that space time which is
exponentially expanding in that manner
is called the sitter space
it's just a very simple solution of
einstein's equations with a positive
cosmological constant incidentally i've
assumed that the vacuum energy here is
positive
right
could it be negative yeah it could be
negative but in fact let's take the case
where it's positive the vacuum energy
density is positive
then
the then this is the solution and when i
say it's the solution i mean to say that
the geometry the tau squared
is equal to dt squared
minus
a squared which is minus
e to the 2h t that's a squared
times the x squared and the x squared
means the x squared plus the y squared
plus dz squared how could it be negative
do you have a positive positive quantity
on the left-hand side yeah
yeah yes you're you're right
it
can't be negative
and space be flat
the um
it can be negative if space is not flat
for example
um
there is the curvature term here plus or
minus one over a squared
uh but you're right the whole thing here
has to be positive
in order that the left-hand side be
positive uh but this can be negative and
this be positive and something else
happened
but
but let's not
belabor that because we're going to take
it to be positive in any case the vacuum
energy to be positive
einstein put his cosmological constant
in to make sure that the universe wasn't
expanding
is that how he did it is he just
well what he did
was to say we know that there's ordinary
energy in the universe so let's put in
plus some constant m over a cubed
and
then
thought about the possibility of
cancellation between this and this also
he put rho naught equal to minus m over
a cubed
okay
it was a mis it was a misstep it didn't
make sense
right but that's that's why he
introduced it in the first place
okay
in any case
this geometry
this geometry which exponentially
expands
distance between any two points
exponentially expands
it has a constant hubble
parameter
is called the sitter space
discovered by the dutch astronomer
wilhelm de sitter
very shortly after einstein
invented his theory
long before
it was known that the universe was
expanding
and
it's an important
space time in cosmology it's important
for two distinct purposes
one of them
is the explanation of the currently
accelerated universe acceleration what
does acceleration mean
it just means uh that the second time
derivative of a
is positive
let's go back to this simple this this
case over here
this of course would be called an
unaccelerated universe because the
second time the derivative of a is just
playing zero
this is accelerated
because the second time derivative of a
uh is positive
and in fact growing
uh with uh
with time
all right so that's the accelerated
universe it's an observed fact
today
this is
a correct description of our universe
not quite
and not quite because there is some
additional energy besides just the
vacuum energy
so let me just remind you quickly what
we know
from observations
we know that the scale factor
in the
past
was this usual t to the two thirds
that's the matter dominated universe
and then at some time
of order a few billion years ago
somewhere is more or less at the halfway
point between now and uh and the big
bang
it uh it began to exponentially increase
or it began to increase more rapidly
now t to the two thirds doesn't look
like that does it
yeah curvature is wrong
t to the two thirds look like that
convexity is wrong
right
and then at some point it
it did start to look like that
and we're somewheres over here
so
this is an observation this is not
something which is speculation
and
there's enough of this curve here that's
been measured
that it does fit neatly on
to the exponential
it itself of course is not quite an
exponential because it's a transitory
behavior
but it appears
to all uh
all observers tend to agree
it looks like it's
entering into an exponential phase
which is another way of saying
that the vacuum energy
is bigger than the other energies
roughly by a factor of two today
but this is getting smaller and smaller
with time and this is not getting
smaller and smaller with time so that's
a current that's our current
understanding
of the universe today
it's exponentially growing
it's the center space
and the hubble constant which is not
exactly constant today because it's not
exactly exponential
but is tending to an exponential
all right that's today
uh
it is also worth discussing the idea of
a horizon i think we've done this before
but let's do it again
it's an important idea
at some
relative coordinate spacing let's call
it delta x
or somewhere some let's not coordinate
spacing at some distance
some actual proper distance
using hubble's law we can calculate the
velocity
as a function of that distance and at
some distance it becomes equal to the
speed of light
all right remember that distance times
hubble
is equal to velocity
and so
if we want the velocity to be the speed
of light then
the distance
that we have to go out to
is equal to the speed of light divided
by that hubble constant the hubble
constant being the square root of a
vacuum energy density the smaller the
vacuum energy density
the smaller h
the bigger the distance to that place
where things are receding away from us
with the speed of light that place of
course is called the horizon
and if you like it's a sphere around us
at a distance given by c over h
numerically
it's about
10 or 12 or 15 billion light years
which accidentally happens to be
about the same as the age of the
universe now whether that's an accident
or not is a matter of very intense
argument
but they're two different quantities one
is the age of the universe
in other words the time where is it i
threw away my graph but
there it is universe started and then
this and we're over here
okay
so
as it happens
this distance scale
apart from a factor of the speed of
light
is about the same as the age of the
universe so the distance is about 10 or
billion light years away and at that
distance as i said this yeah
isn't it hubble isn't the tangent line
to the uh at any point if it happens to
intersect the origin then those two
quantities will
uh
coincidentally be the same
in other words
distances
that of course would be exactly true for
a of t equals t
right
yeah
okay
so at the moment it is a bit of a
mystery
why the vacuum energy happens to be
such okay
that the distance to the horizon
or
converted to a time
by means of the speed of light
why
the distance to the horizon
is about the same as the distance
uh to the surface of the surface of last
scattering but if you like to the age of
the universe
not knowing exactly why that's true
coincidence as far as we know
well it's not remaining the same either
the horizon is a change the
the hubble constant is remaining the
same of course the age of the universe
is not remaining the same right
right so as far so it sounds like it's a
coincidence of just us be being here at
the time that we're here
right let's tell you let's take it to be
just a coincidence
now is it a coincidence is it a
coincidence that the darwinian time
scale for evolution happens to be the
same
as the time scale
as obtained from
the vacuum energy
no that's clearly something which we
have to explain someday
in the in the center space
is that assuming that there's no matter
or and no no radiation yeah
okay that one happens to this
we have a situation where
the
so i guess there's a form of energy this
fact can you say something about this
documentary because i'm
pretty confused about what its source is
or what it is
i mean you would think that if you
didn't have any matter or radiation
you'd get nothing
i mean naively right
so for that we have to understand why
quantum mechanics
gives energy
to the ground state of systems the
vacuum is the ground state
of let's say quantum field theory ground
state means the state of lowest energy
now
in
the vacuum
it's possible to have oscillations of
electric and magnetic fields and so
forth
the oscillations behave like ordinary
oscillations and ordinary oscillations
have a ground state energy
the ground state energy is not zero and
the reason that it's not zero is because
of the heisenberg uncertainty principle
we're going off track but let's answer
the question anyway if we have a
harmonic oscillator what's the potential
of a harmonic oscillator
the energy of it
is proportional to the momentum square
that's the kinetic energy i'm not going
to put in numerical factors
plus the distance squared
that you stretch the spring so to speak
all right there's usually a factor of
spring constant here and a factor of one
over twice the mass here but just leave
it like this this is good enough for us
p squared plus x squared now
classically the ground state of the
harmonic oscillator simply means the
configuration in which the spring
is at its equilibrium point
not vibrating not stretched to sitting
at its equilibrium point
x equals zero
and because the velocity of it is also
equal to zero at the equilibrium point p
is equal to zero and the energy is equal
to zero p squared plus x squared both of
these terms are equal to zero
the heisenberg
principle does not allow there to be a
state in which
both x and p are simultaneously
knowable
in the language of quantum mechanics
diagonalizable
and so there's a necessary fluctuation
if x were literally right at the center
here
then p would have to have an infinite
fluctuation
if p were at the center
in other words if the momentum was
exactly equal to zero then x would have
to have an infinite uncertainty
and so there is no state of the system
in which both p and x are exactly known
to be equal to 0 they both fluctuate but
the sum of p squared plus x squared
doesn't necessarily have to fluctuate
but it's got to be positive
since both p and x cannot simultaneously
be zero
the vacuum or the ground state energy of
a harmonic oscillator is not zero now
what is it what is the ground state
energy of a harmonic oscillator
one-half
h-bar
omega where omega is the frequency of
the oscillator
now the universe is full of potential
harmonic oscillators
full of harmonic oscillators they're the
oscillations of the electromagnetic
field
there's in fact an infinite number of
them
of low frequency
high frequency
and a large number of such oscillations
not just the electromagnetic field but
every field
and every field has a ground state
energy it's the energy
stored in that field
due to
zero point oscillations
every every field behaves like an
oscillator every field has zero point
energy and it's those zero point
energies which are
one
explanation of the vacuum energy
the real puzzle is why it's so small
it is very small numerically very small
but uh
that is not for tonight
let's just recognize that it exists
as the universe expands it doesn't
dilute
it's just a constant
and experimentally it really is or
observationally it really does seem to
be there with a particular numerical
constant
which happens to be extremely small
measured in natural units
i have an idea why isn't that just the
the last scattering baseline energy
i don't know what that means i just mean
that there's
there's always
a
three degree
it's not the three degree radiation
that's radiation
that energy decreases with time because
the photons dilute
and furthermore each photon decreases
its energy it's not the three degree
it's the oscillations that are there
when you remove
all the for all the real photons
it's
the virtual photons or the just the zero
point oscillation that uh that is
necessarily
present
of course we're not now talking about a
particle on the end of a spring
we're talking about the fluctuations of
the electromagnetic field
in fact you know what these two things
would be for the electromagnetic field
which uh which can't for which there's
an uncertainty principle well isn't this
like sources
electric and magnetic fields
the energy of an electromagnetic field
is e squared plus b squared
with e being
like momentum
and b squared
and there's an uncertainty principle
between electric and magnetic fields
which is very similar to the uncertainty
relation between velocity or momentum
and position
okay so they can't both simultaneously
be zero
because of an uncertainty relation
between them
and the result is
that even when you remove as much energy
as is possible to remove from the field
there's still this residual zero point
energy that's what constitutes or at
least that's what's believed to be the
origin of this
i'm starting a tough time understanding
if you remove matter and you remove
radiation
what causes the electric fields
like
what's the perturbation and what
i can't answer what causes it
i can tell you that the uncertainty
principle requires it to be there
but we're making the assumption there is
no electric field there is no mass
i thought you did i say there's no
electric field so sitter space has only
the uh the dark energy
okay
it has no real photons
it has only the zero point energy okay
you can have an electric field without
real pulling it just doesn't have any
charges
it's there anyway the field fluctuates
anyway it doesn't need charges right
all right
yeah
could you go over that point about the
age of the universe being equal to the
uh inverse hubble constant
yeah okay let's take a look i know it is
equal to inverse total constant but it's
also equal to the
distance to the surface the last
scattering
oh that's that's an approximation that's
the distance to the surface of last
scattering but uh
um
isn't that just a
mathematical truism
just because of the equations it's just
yeah
it's not an experimental effect
um
almost
almost yeah
but not that h not that h is
approximately the age of the universe no
clearly it does not have to be
in this deciduous space it's simply not
true
h just never changes the age of the
universe does change
it's exactly true
it's only exactly true
for this scale factor over here let's
see why
all right let's let's take this case
a of t
grows like t
then what is h h is equal to a dot over
a
what is a dot
a dot is 1
and t and a is t so this is just equal
to 1 over t and it's clear that the
hubble constant it's not constant but
the hubble parameter is just one over
the time
the time from the big bang
any power law well it's not quite true
take any power law here
then it becomes then a dot
is equal to p
t to the p minus one
and then divide that by a
that means dividing it by t to the p and
the answer is p over t
so for example if p is two-thirds then
this would be two-thirds
over t
and it would not quite be the case that
the hubble constant was one over time
but it would be one over time with a
factor of two-thirds in front of it yeah
but i'm assuming there's other constants
we're not including anyway all right
that's right three so there will be
three halves in front of it
eight should be three-halves one over t
oh did i write the uh
one over p so
no that's right two thirds is right but
h
is right
okay
yeah two-thirds is right
that's h left-hand side is h for the d
sitter universe it's infinite wait okay
wait h is equal
to 2 2 over 3
t where t is the age of the universe at
any given time
okay now let's come to the descender
case
the decider case
is not
t to the p
it is
e it's exponential
e to the ht
let's not call it h okay let's just call
it e to the
constant gamma t
all right a is e to the gamma t
what is a dot
incidentally i could put a constant in
front of it it wouldn't make any
difference let's put the constant in
front of it what is a dot
a dot is c
gamma e to the gamma t right
just differentiated e to the gamma t
now divide it by that's a dot
divided by a which is just c that
cancels c and it cancels e to the gamma
t
so we find out that the hubble constant
now is truly constant and it's just this
gamma which appears here
okay this is the unique case in which
the hubble constant is constant
it's the only case where it's constant
uh
once we know
that the hub that that a dot over a
let's go back a dot over a
is equal to the square root of 8 pi g
over 3
times rho this is the square root of the
frw equation
all right so the hubble constant is just
the square root
of 8 pi g over 3
times the vacuum energy that's h
right so there's a definite connection
between this vacuum energy on the one
hand
and the hubble rate of expansion we call
it sometimes the rate of excel the
hubble rate of expansion it's the thing
that goes in here
it tells us
in this case
1 over h is not the age of the universe
what is it
it's the time constant it's a time that
it takes the universe to double and not
double in size but multiply by e yeah
the time that it takes for the universe
to double
i said double again let me use double
but i really mean multiply by e
it's the
time constant for the universe to double
in size
and what is that
that is
the inverse of this h and it's about 10
billion
years okay so every 10 billion years
we can expect the universe will double
in size roughly roughly speaking that's
an approximation
this vacuum energy density is constant
right yeah it's constant well
yes
this of course is an experimental
question okay so if the universe is
expanding
so that applies to me that the energy
the total energy vacuum energy is
increasing
where is it coming from
it's coming from the other side of the
equation
this minus this is equal to zero
this is one form of energy this is
another form of energy this is a kind of
kinetic energy of expansion
it's kind of kinetic energy of expansion
uh
both terms appear in the expression for
the energy and in general relativity
and
it's conserved because it's equal to
zero
so it's by so this energy is coming from
here
that comes from einstein's field
equations if you apply einstein if you
apply the ideas of hamiltonians and
energy to einstein's field equations
we talked about all that kinetic energy
at the beginning yes right so is that
basically being transferred
yeah it's a transfer of kinetic and
potential energy
when we talk about energy being
conserved or entropy increasing are we
talking entropy or energy
either one okay are we talking about
that within the cosmic horizon or do we
mean
the cosmic horizon
is fixed in size
it doesn't change with time
that's the same statement that the
hubble constant doesn't change with time
the energy within the cosmic horizon
stays fixed with time
the vacuum energy the vacuum energy is
just the volume of this
times the vacuum energy density
the vacuum energy density which is rho
naught let's let's just let's work it
out
um
okay so that's this diameter here which
is what is it
uh
c divided by
square root
of 8
pi g over 3
times the square root of rho naught in
the denominator
that's the distance now i want to what i
want to do with it i want to cube it in
order to find the volume
cubed
yeah four thirds four thirds pi
okay and then multiply that by the
vacuum energy density and the vacuum
energy density is rho naught itself
there's some amount of energy in there
but it doesn't change with time it
doesn't change with time the amount
within the cosmic horizon so the portion
that we can see
the portion that we can ever see
uh that energy doesn't change with time
if it's the sitter space right if it's
the center space
right
so
you know standing here from our vantage
point
and looking out and looking at all the
vacuum energy that's out there no it
doesn't change with time the portion
that we can see
okay
good so that's that's the basic idea of
a cosmic horizon
things can pass through the cosmic
horizon in the same sense that they can
pass through a black hole horizon
and i won't go into that in any depth
now
but uh
once they do
they're out of contact with us and
they're gone
so if it's not at the space
does that mean that energy
flows
beside the customer
to energy within the cost of horizon it
might
well energy is energy is a loaded term
exactly what do you mean by the energy
in general relativity in general
relativity
the concept of energy is a little bit
curious because it contains this
gravitational component as well as
ordinary energy
this is the gravitational component of
the energy here
for this particularly simple kind of uh
geometry
yeah let's uh
let's move on
all right now the same
the same mechanism
appears to have happened in the remote
past
but instead of the time constant being
about 10 billion years
it was about 10 to the minus 32 seconds
or perhaps that that fast where does
this come from well
the origin of the question this is
inflation this is the idea of inflation
the universe and the remote past
exponentially expanded now when i say
this happened of course to some extent
this is conjectural
but the conjecture has passed a number
of observational tests so when i say
something has happened
you can feel free to put a little bit of
a question mark did it really happen or
or am i guessing
okay so i will tell you what's known and
what the empirical evidence is but let
me just shorten my sentences by saying
something happened it's all right
it
happened that in the remote past before
anything that we can observe
in other words out beyond the surface of
last scattering or earlier than the time
when the universe became transparent
universe was exponentially expanding now
why did that idea gain any traction and
where did it come from
well the basic place that it came from
was the flatness of the universe to make
a long story short
spatially the space
slices of the universe
are rather flat
flat meaning we don't seem to live in a
curved universe which is either
positively curved or negatively curved
we seem to live in a very flat universe
in fact not only a flat universe but a
rather homogeneous universe
on large scales bigger than
superclusters of galaxies in particular
on the largest scales
the universe is very flat and
homogeneous and smooth
how did it get to be that way and why is
it that way
the early ideas of the big bang were
that the universe started just in some
random state
it
could have started
with some very complex geometry it
didn't have to be flat and it didn't
have to be homogeneous we don't really
have a theory of how it began in the
very very beginning
but let's suppose it began like a
shriveled up raisin
or prune
with all sorts of wiggles and texture to
it right why what is where did all those
wiggles and texture go where did it
disappear to now in fact we know here's
something we know
we know at the time of the surface of
last scattering in other words at what
we ordinarily think of as the big bang
the beginning
the beginning as far as we can see back
already at that time the universe was
very flat and smooth
so it's not that it flattened itself out
and stretched itself out between the big
bang and now big bang i mean
looking back to the surface of less
scattering the surface of less
scattering itself is very smooth which
indicates that at the time when the
universe was as hot as the surface of
the sun
it was already very smooth so something
had smoothed it out
now you might say why do you need
something to smooth it out just
postulate that it started out smooth
okay you can do that
uh
and but in fact it wasn't exactly smooth
we'll come to the deviations from
smoothness
but the question was asked why is it
that the universe started so very smooth
why is it that the density in one place
is about the same as the density in a
very very different place
in particular we can imagine places
which are so far apart
that light we can we can see them both
all right we can see them but we see
something way out there and something
way out there
but we know that light did not have time
to get from one to the
other so there was no way
that a smoothing process could have
happened on such large scales
and what is it that made the universe
smooth and flat on those scales well the
hypothesis is
that the big that what we ordinarily
call the big bang that there was a
prehistory to it and during the
prehistory of it
the universe exponentially expanded
by an enormous amount and got itself
stretched out to be almost completely
flat likely inflation of a balloon
i i like to think of it that way you
start with a completely deflated balloon
and the completely deflated balloon
looks uh
looks like a uh
um
you know what a completely deflated
balloon looks like okay
it has all sorts of uh
wrinkles a wrinkle a wrinkly balloon a
really wrinkly balloon
and now you start blowing it up
and after it's expanded a certain number
of times it gets pretty
homogeneous it gets pretty smooth
okay
so
if there was and this prehistory would
have had to be before the surface of
last scattering because it's known it
was already very smooth at that time
right
what was the hypothesis the hypothesis
was
called inflation due to alan guth in the
era in the early 80s around 1980
that the universe underwent
at that very early time
a period of exponential inflation
exponential growth in other words
that for a period it behaved like the
sitter space are we assuming equilibrium
before inflation no
no
whatever inflation does it stretches
things out so much that you lose memory
of what the structure might have been
like before inflation started
it just takes whatever was there and
stretches it out so much
that it just leaves it in this very very
homogeneous configuration there was no
previous homogeneity
we don't know
one of the good thing about inflation is
it erases all the initial conditions and
so you don't have to know what the
initial conditions is because
you don't have to know what the balloon
looked like in the beginning because it
gets stretched out the bad thing about
inflation is it erases
all the information about how it started
i don't know i mean if you had a blotch
on the on a raisin and you blew it up
then you would still have a blotch now
you're blowing it up to something very
much bigger than the size of the known
universe so imagine there was a blotch
on the raisin
and
the raisin got to be 10 to the 10 to the
10 to the 10 times bigger than the
observed universe exponentially remember
the idea was it was exponentially
growing
so it got to be 10 to the 10 to the 10
to the 10 to 10 times bigger than the
observable universe so it's just as if
the surface becomes transparent
from previously okay or something it's
not transparent it just it just gets
stretched out it just gets stretched out
so that that
blot or that
blob that
little bit of inhomogeneity
got stretched out
it's still there but it's there on a
scale much much bigger than we can see
okay
but you have to assume that it wasn't
sort of a fractal to start right because
in that case you wouldn't even you know
yeah you had to assume
that uh that there was smoothness on
some terribly tiny scale
but if the universe
expanded enough if it inflated enough
then if you start on any scale with some
fluctuation it will eventually stretch
that fluctuation out
that's known as inflation
and the hypothesis is
that in the very early universe
that basically exactly the same kind of
thing happened that is happening today
except with a hubble constant at that
time
which was millions and millions of times
larger
larger yes larger in other words with a
vacuum energy which was very much larger
than the vacuum energy that we see today
okay now that's a curious idea it's a
crazy idea why was the vacuum energy
different then than it is now can we
even call it the vacuum energy if it was
if it had to do
with something which is different than
the vacuum today
and what's the basic idea
all right so the basic idea goes
something like this now we do have to
talk i'm going to tell you what the idea
is and then we'll come back at some
point i hope and discuss what the
empirical evidence for this idea
at first it was just almost a throwaway
idea maybe something like this happened
and
as time went on
observation got better and better
to the point where this picture has been
pretty well confirmed by now that
doesn't mean it's absolutely got to be
right
it means that it's the best candidate
for our understanding of what happened
all right to understand you have to you
have to have the idea of a scalar field
a scalar field is a field just like
maxwell's field just like electric and
magnetic field
except instead of being a vector at
every point in space the electric and
magnetic fields are vectors they have
direction at every point in space it's
just a scalar
no sense of directionality
and let's call that field let's give it
a name let's call it phi
is it any of the fields that we see in
nature today
is it
identified
is it are its quanta identified with any
of the known particles definitely not
definitely not it is not identified with
any observed fields that we know about
in
in physics
and its quanta are not identified with
any known particles so it's a
hypothetical field
which exists in fill space
same way as any other field
uh and it has an energy it has an energy
associated with it
the energy that's associated with it is
a kind of potential energy
and a potential energy
that scalar fields can have
and it's a potential energy
v
which the v is
standard terminology for a potential
energy it doesn't when i say it's a
potential energy i mean it doesn't have
to do with the time derivative of phi
of course there's energy in a field if
it's oscillating if it's fluctuating
but there also can be energy in a field
just because the field
is displaced away from zero value
we'll find now this this
for the moment let's completely forget
about quantum mechanics quantum
mechanics is not important to the
discussion right now
and it's some potential energy called
vfi
vfi is some function of phi
let's just draw some picture of it
here's some picture of it
any function whatever function you like
you can put in here
and uh
of course you get a different theory out
no matter what function you put in here
but imagine some function of phi
then
if phi is one value or another value or
another value or another value
the field energy and it's a kind of
vacuum energy it's a kind of energy
that's there not really in the vacuum
but there
simply by virtue of having some space in
which there is a field which takes on a
particular value it's very similar to
vacuum energy
via phi
but it can vary
as a question about that drawing is that
what's the act the horizontal axis is
sorry phi and the vertical axis really
okay right
all right
now you have to you have to you're
buying a whole uh
set of ideas here which none of which
are obvious
first of all that there can exist scalar
fields in nature this is not obvious
that they have potential energy well the
mathematics of field theory suggests
that they that they can and do have
potential energy
and the potential energy can vary from
point to point so different values of
the field can have different energies
right
but one also has to take it as a matter
of uh
you have to take it as a matter of faith
i take it as a matter of known
mathematics that vfi
if phi is not changing
for example if it just has some value
over here
is a kind of vacuum energy
it's a kind of vacuum energy
which doesn't dilute that's the main
property of it it doesn't dilute
this part of the energy of a field
doesn't dilute
yeah the the
if you drew a picture of space then
would fly be constant over the space it
may or may not be constant
yeah it could have different values in
different places
that's right let's for the moment
suppose that it was the same everywheres
let's take that case for the moment all
right we take that case for the moment
and we say what would the world be like
let's say what would what
also
phi itself is a function of x y z and t
in principle it could be a function of x
y z and t
let's take the case for the moment where
it's just constant
for whatever reason
at some value of phi
then in effect the world has a vacuum
energy which is just v at that value of
phi
that's the way scalar field energies
work
they behave exactly like vacuum energy
in particular they don't dilute
so then if that were the case we would
simply say that the vacuum energy
is replaced by
v of phi
where phi is the value that the field
happens to have it might be over here
might be over here as long as it's not
changing with space or time it would
just be a constant
phi being constant in space
and then we would go back to all the
equations for the sitter space or all
the equations for the expansion of the
universe
and every place we saw rho naught
we would stick v of phi
in particular the universe would expand
with a hubble constant
which would be equal to the square root
of 8 pi over 3
g and instead of rho naught i would
write v
of phi
now what happens if v of phi if i varies
from place to place
supposing over here it's a different
value than it is over here
or different value than it is over here
well first
let's go back to the case where it's not
varying
what's happening where it's not varying
the region of space over which it's not
varying is expanding
exponentially like e to the ht
what happens if it varies from place to
place
then in different places
it's expanding
expanding with different time constants
but stretching
exponentially
by an amount that depends on v at every
place so if v is varying or phi is
varying from place to place
you would have exponential expansion
everywhere
but a different time constant in each
place
right but if the universe expands enough
if it inflates enough if it stretches
enough
and you're inside there someplace and
you can only see out to your horizon
eventually the stretching is so much
that your entire
environment your entire environment
has been stretched out to the point
where the field within your region has
become homogeneous has become constant
so it's very much like this balloon
the balloon could be painted with some
color which varies from place to place
red over here blue over here purple in
between
and then you expand it out inflate it
out by many many orders of magnitude
and somebody at the center or somebody
at some point who only can see so far
sees a very homogeneous color
all right
same thing with this inflating universe
v might vary from place to place
but if it does vary from place to place
it will get stretched out in such a way
that that it will look for practical
purposes as if it were very constant
now it would worry me though if uh
very let's say
you know very proportional to something
in other words
it's not what you seem to have drawn is
a situation where fear is constant and
patches
and it seems to me like it could be
it doesn't have to be constant just
slowly varying slowly slowly
slowly varying on what feet on what
scale
well it doesn't matter much because
whatever scale it's slowly varying on
eventually that scale will get stretched
out
now you could imagine maybe it was so
bad to begin with that it would never
stretch out
you could imagine that but apparently
that's not the way it was
and that we judge because the universe
is today rather homogeneous
right
so
let me draw for you
then the way
experiment
various combinations of observations
suggests this via fi to be oh ins yeah
all right
incidentally if you have a potential
energy function which looks like that
it could be the potential energy instead
of for a field it could be for a
coordinate of some kind
what happens if you start the coordinate
over here
what happens if you start a particle
in a potential energy and you start over
here
you roll down
now
uh let's suppose you start up here
you roll down you roll over the hill you
roll over the hill and you eventually
go somewhere else
if there's a lot of friction
if there's a lot of friction you might
roll down the hill here
and just get stuck at the minimum
um
the minimum
really are places the minima
really are places where the field would
just be constant
if you started the field over here it
really wouldn't be constant it would it
might roll down
if there was friction and there is
friction in cosmology if there was
friction
then it might just come to rest at the
bottom over here if it comes to rest at
the bottom
if the field comes to rest then it's
constant
that's the situation in which you can
pretend that the field is very constant
and doesn't change with time
if it's sitting
at the minimum
of the potential
it could come to rest in any of these
all right so here is what it is thought
that the potential energy
of some
field which we have never discovered
we've never measured it
it is a
conjectural speculative
construction
with a field energy with a v that looks
something like this now
perhaps it starts
with a shape of some unknown kind
but then it gets very flat
not completely flat
question
so the field energy doesn't vary for
very much over some range of phi
and then all of a sudden it comes to the
end of a cliff comes to a cliff
and falls down
it doesn't quite go to zero
and then turns back up
now this is so ridiculous
that um
so contrived let's put it this way it is
so contrived
that it almost
seems quite ridiculous
nevertheless this is what observational
cosmology seems to demand so here's the
picture
the universe
started
in some unknown way in a way that we
don't know
with a field energy vfi
that was located on a plateau like this
because
this was almost a flat plateau
phi didn't change very much with time
it changed very slowly like being on a
very very shallow like this eraser on
the table top here
uh
there's enough friction and in fact in
cosmology there was a lot of friction
that the eraser doesn't move very much
you could tilt the you could tilt the uh
the table quite a bit before you would
start to move off
um
the kind of friction is not quite the
same as the kind of friction on this
table here
yeah more like a viscosity yeah more
like a fluid viscosity
this is called slip stick
friction which means it sticks until it
slips
all right motion of an object through a
liquid or gas
uh is a better analog for what happens
uh for cosmology
so but there is a kind of viscosity
viscosity is the right picture there is
a kind of viscosity that's particularly
associated
with
with an expanding universe
and the faster the expansion the bigger
the viscosity
and so if this were a particle
moving on a potential energy surface
like this in other words just a
potential like this it would slowly
slowly slowly move down here
under the combined
effect
of the slope of the potential that means
a little bit of a push in this direction
and at the same time the viscosity would
keep it moving slowly
it would stay at this level
for a long period of time
during that time v didn't change much
so v was almost constant during that
time
and if v were constant
then it would just be a constant vacuum
energy
so to the extent
that the universe slid down this hill
very slowly
and the vacuum energy didn't change much
then during that period the universe
inflated during that period the universe
exponentially grew and it exponentially
grew with a time constant that looks
like this
where v of phi
was just the value of v along here
a very big value right what's that a
very big value well it depends on what
units you're measuring it of course
so if you're measuring it in ordinary
everyday units
it's enormous
even if you're measuring it in
elementary particle units it's very very
large but if you're measuring it in
plank units it must have been it was
very small
so it depends on what unit you're
talking about but
in
units anything like the density of
energy in this room
it's it's humongously big
right so very very large energy here
what's causing phi to move
it's changing the slope of the potential
the slope of the potential is causing it
to slowly drift down that hill
roughly as if
roughly as if you had a weak
gravitational field
forget the talking about ordinary
gravity imagine this room were filled
with liquid filled with honey
and you put a rock in it
the gravitational field would correspond
to a tilt in the potential energy
potential energy higher at one end than
at the other end higher up there than it
is here
the viscosity of the honey
would lead to the rock falling and it
would fall slowly with a terminal
velocity
all right so this slowly slides down
here
assuming the slope is small enough
until it gets to the edge and at the
edge here it suddenly goes over the edge
and winds up eventually down here
okay what does eventually mean
eventually means today isn't that more
like slipstick
no
no no it doesn't it never sticks well i
mean
it looks like it's slipping he's
slipping
no stick though
right it's not just at the station right
i always thought a slip stick was a
thing but a slip stick wasn't the thing
the slip was slip or stick
slider with a
slider
do they call it that yeah so they do
okay
okay yeah
i guess from my engineering background i
thought a slip stick was a thing
but no this it's a it's an adjective
slip stick friction
all right it's not slip stick it's just
slip
or viscosity
and then when it gets to the end here
all of a sudden
the potential energy changes rapidly
that means effectively that there's a
large force on the universe pushing it
over the hill here
and what happens when it gets down here
when it gets down here at the minimum it
comes to rest comes the rest the
combination of friction
and minimum potential energy it comes to
rest where are we today we're down at
the bottom
how do i know
what the height of this potential energy
is because i know today what the uh what
the hubble constant is
so the hubble constant is 8 pi 3 over g
v of phi
that's the exponential growth of the
universe today
and that appears to be down here
the coefficient down here is very very
small much much smaller than it was up
here
why this is true we don't know we really
don't know
but we do know what the potential energy
is at the bottom here
because we know today what the hubble
constant is today
right
and it's very small
we also suspect
and there's some evidence
that the potential energy up here was
very much larger
and that the universe that the hubble
constant was very much larger
in other words that the doubling time of
the universe was many orders of
magnitude larger than this one doubling
every 10 to the 10th years
in fact with standard cosmology
cosmological numbers
uh
this inflation took place with a time
constant of 10 to the minus 32 seconds
or something like that so it's kind of
crazy i mean this is a crazy picture
this is a crazy picture the amazing
thing is that it that it seems to have
some validity
we gradually drifted down here
and came to the edge and went down to
here
the expansion that took place
up in here is called inflation
it's called inflation
where did the big bang happen
incidentally
the thing that we normally call the big
bang
the big bang happened after
we got pretty much down to here
after we slid over this edge
the big bang meaning to say what i mean
by the big bang now is the surface of
last scattering
the surface of last scattering was very
late in this picture
it happened
well after the universe settled down
here
so the big bang and everything we
actually can observe about cosmology was
down in here
but before the big bang happened
this
period of exponential inflation took
place according to theory
and during that period the universe
stretched itself out so much
that all of the wrinkles disappeared if
you like
so that means that the universe at the
time of the big bang or the time of the
surface of last scatting was already
stretched out by many many powers of e
how many powers of e that we don't know
for sure you can ask a question here uh
the wrinkles are mainly wrinkles in the
in this primordial
scale
then or and also the gravitational field
also the gravitational field yeah
in other words the shape of space and
its curvature might have been
fluctuating but also fine
yeah what is the x-axis is that t or a
problem
why
here in this
phi the field phi
this is the potential energy as a
function of the field phi
the field phi
can depend on time
as the universe rolls down this hill
well it's sort of what acts like a time
parameter like a what it's acting like a
time parameter here because you've got a
monotonic function
it is in fact acting like a time
parameter
uh
this is true
time parameter meaning to say that it's
monotonic function of time
yeah what is the part after that
all we know is that we're living at some
place where the potential energy is not
quite
zero yeah
nothing in our experience tells us very
much about here
looking back in the past
we discover something that looks like a
motion like this
we're going to come to what the to what
the observational evidence for this is
but uh this may be a bad analogy but
when you're looking at gravitationally
derived potential energy it's a function
of position
but holding potential energy in the
presence of a gravitational fielder
weightlessness there is no a
gravitational field simply in this
context means a gradient of the
potential energy well where what is the
analog of a gravitational field in this
picture
where is there one
okay let's not get ourselves confused
between gravity
as the real thing in this universe
and the model that i was describing of a
rock falling through uh through honey
right right
some force on a system
uh which pushes it from one place to
another basically
that's the gradient of the potential
energy here the fact that it's not
actually exactly flat
just in case it was not clear this was
not intended to be exactly flat it was
intended to have a small slope
it's analogous to the table having a
small slope
if the table has a small slope then the
potential energy differs from point to
point
and if something is on this table if
there's no friction what happens if
there's no friction
it starts accelerating
okay
what happens if there's some viscosity
it reaches a terminal velocity it starts
to accelerate but then reaches a
terminal velocity and just moves slowly
across the table
if the table has a small tilt
it will move slowly
okay
it'll move slowly until it gets to the
edge of the table
okay
and then it falls off
so it doesn't oscillate
well it may oscillate down at the bottom
here
that's dark that dark energy dark matter
today
all right the big bang and everything we
historically know about the universal
all took place after
this got
down to very close to the bottom here
also down at the bottom
it fell down this and just stuck there
not stuck because of stick slip but
stuck because it's the minimum of the
energy and what is the period of
inflation this balloon is expanding is
that just the clip or the whole thing no
no the whole thing here
and that's about t to the minus
by a minus
two six
that
right
minus thirty two seconds
doubling every 10 to the minus 32
seconds
now that may seem very fast
but on the scale on the plunk scale and
units over plunk time it's very slow in
fact
the plunk time is 10 to the minus 42
seconds this is
yeah right we don't know how long this
was and so we don't know how long this
inflation took place
so we don't know in that sense whether
it expanded by a factor of
10 to the 10 to the 10 10 to the 10 to
the 10 10 to the 10 to the 10 to the 10
to the 10
we don't know
all that information got wiped out by
this expansion
now what happened what did this
expansion do
it did exactly the same thing that it
would do to a balloon
it flattens it
and it leads to a situation
where by the time
you get to here incidentally
falling off the edge here is called
reheating
there's nothing really about it it
should just be called heating
but it's called reheating
why is it called reheating
this happened rather suddenly
when a thing like this happens rather
suddenly
the energy that was stored in the field
is rather quickly converted to some
other form of energy
when you fell off the cliff here just
like that eraser when it hit the floor
there
its energy its potential energy was
converted to heat
then
as you roll over the edge here and by
the time you get down to the bottom the
universe is hot
it wasn't hot up here
in fact any heat that might have been
there to begin with was diluted by this
enormous
exponential exponential exponential
factor
so if there was some thermal energy to
begin with
the universe simply expanded so much
that it got diluted to the point of uh
so that's why it's reheating that first
curve up there represents an injection
of heat well
or something
right right but we all we also know we
know nothing about that
right
it's a hist
you're perfectly right that perhaps in
the very early prehistory something
happened over here that was heating
and then
reheating
but we know nothing about this really we
can't observe this directly all right we
can't or
it's hard to observe we don't know if we
can observe it but we don't think it's
lower
right
right so how we go how the universe got
up here why it started up there we don't
know
but we know that if it did start up here
and it stayed up there long enough that
the initial conditions
are sort of wiped out or that diluted so
much
that we have no
fossil memory of them everything started
very very stretched out which means the
universe was extremely homogeneous now
this is going to be qualified we're
going to qualify the statement
i'm oversimplifying a little bit sort of
on purpose
if
the universe expanded by a factor of 10
to the 10 to the 10th
then it would look extremely flat
by the time you got to here
that's the reason we believe
that the right solution of the
cosmological equations today involves
flat space remember i told you earlier
on
that observationally
the
curvature term
this
factor k which can be
plus or minus one or zero
is observationally zero
meaning to say that the universe looks
spatially flat
to about one percent or beta better than
one percent but it seems to be spatially
very very flat
geometry of space seems to be euclidean
geometry why is this so
well to the best of our knowledge there
was a period of expansion
which flattened everything out
so that
we are today looking at the universe
on a scale which is very much smaller
than its curvature
we might as well use flat space
because the universe radius of curvature
is so much bigger than the region we can
see
all right
now good question yeah when you say 10
to the 10th century or is that just an
arbitrary number or do you mean it at
least that big i i
we don't know we don't know anything
about how long have we remained up here
we don't we don't know how wide this
plateau is and we don't know how shallow
it is
the shallower it is in the higher we
don't we actually don't know how high it
is
we don't know how broad it is and we
don't know how
all right we have some bounds we have
some bounds
we know something about the combination
of these parameters and basically what
we know
is that the universe
doubled or got multiplied by a factor of
e
at least about 50 times do we know e to
the 50th
do we have any idea how much energy got
put in
to the system
uh
we have some bounds on it we have some
bounds on it
that's another way of asking what the
height of this is
yeah yeah we have some bounds on it um
i would say the best bet would be
something like about 10 to the minus 14
in planck units but that's a huge amount
of energy in ordinary units
so you want me to give it to you in
joules well i can't give it to you in
joules without sitting down doing a
calculation but it's 10 to a large
number 10 to the 90th or something
why did the universe reheat after the
expansion slowed down well it reheated
because it came to the edge of this
cliff and that potential energy was
converted
at first into
kinetic energy of the motion of the
field
just as this eraser
that's potential energy got converted to
kinetic energy
and then when it hit the floor
where that energy go to
well it went into thermal energy
it went into thermal energy uh
and that thermal energy is the energy
that uh
that the universe had at the big bang
yeah you made some sort of comment about
dark matter uh some connection with dark
matter
you could ask might this feel of
oscillated here
that oscillation energy
conceivably could be
the energy of dark matter it would get
diluted the energy of
let's not get into that that the i did
say that but the
this is not the important lesson here
can you say anything about the actual
value of fee at the present which is to
say at the at that v minute
phi
you mean this distance
v or phi
these vertical
fee is horizontal
what is the value of v relative to
row zero
no
no no no no
v has the same units as row zero
that's v
all right
exactly that's row zero
very small could you plot phi as a
function of time
yeah
i could plot it but let me just draw it
instead i mean let me just put my finger
on here to follow it
maybe it came we don't know very much
about this but it slipped down here and
then very very very slowly inched along
here
while it was inching along here
things were exponentially growing
and eventually it got to here and
perhaps it oscillated a few times at the
bottom
but there was a good deal of friction at
the bottom due to the expansion of the
universe
and so eventually it just came to rest
at the bottom
and then t goes on the tree stays still
right
okay
in other words
as when you get down to the bottom here
you've gotten on to this branch of
things
which is today's current deciduous base
uh behavior
now do we know for sure that that it
comes to rest here
no but
but we know that it's moving slowly
so
this is this is a model of what we we
know
we know fragments of this we don't know
the whole picture
with any great certainty but we know
some fragments
we know for example that this is not
zero
so the universe is exponentially
inflating today but with this very long
time constant
we know that it was rather high over
here
many orders of magnitude larger than it
is today
and so the universe
did apparently i have not talked about
the observational evidence yet
but the observational evidence and
indicates that
along here the universe grew by at least
a factor of
e i said e to the 50
usually it's quoted as e to the 60
and
but
you can you can play with the numbers a
little bit
so
the universe is e to the 60 times bigger
than it was
over here
at least at minimum
now how many times
incidentally the number of times
that it got multiplied by e
is called the number of e-foldings e
foldings
and e fold simply means multiplication
by e
each of which took uh
10 to the minus 32 seconds but that also
that number
is dependent on the height here and the
height is not well known
the height is not well known what's
known
is that
there was at least about e to the 50 or
more e-foldings sorry 50 or more
e-foldings
is it possible that the uh that that it
was absolute that was flat on the top
and that there was just sort of the
perturbations of the field which
flipped it off the edge if it's too flat
on the top
yeah
it's not
it's not consistent that it was
completely flat
it had to have some tilt but uh but it
could be pretty close to flat no
possibility for some kind of quantum
effect to flip it off to the well flip
it off the cliff yeah yeah yeah yeah no
no no definitely definitely
so that you would just have uni
sort of in this vast matrix of nothing
you'd have a universe here if it were
too flat at the top
if it was the two flat at the top it
would have created two in homogeneous
universe
which was what i was about to explain
right okay so we know that it could have
been too flat on the top so let me
explain how we know that
first of all
i said
this is an interesting story with many
parts and i i will not try to get to
them all now
but uh
what i said was the universe inflates
and the process of inflating
becomes homogeneous homogeneous on any
ordinary scale
on a scale
let's say as big as the horizon size
that's not terribly big it may have had
many more e-foldings than that it may
have been stretched out by many many
times
bigger than that in the same sense that
the earth is much bigger than the
horizon that we can see from
six feet above the earth incidentally
what is the horizon from six feet above
the earth
a couple of miles i think yeah
the earth is much bigger than that in
the same sense our horizon
not in the same sense but in an
analogous sense our horizon
is rather small on the scale of the
radius of curvature of the universe
which means it expanded and inflated
many times larger than the uh than the
region that we can see
okay so it got to be by by this process
of stretching
it got to be very very homogeneous
except for one thing
one thing prevented it from becoming
completely homogeneous
and that was
quantum fluctuations
now
we i we could we can delve into this a
little more deeply
but not tonight
quantum fluctuations created just
quantum mechanical fluctuations
take what would have become an
infinitely stretched out completely
homogeneous universe
and leave over quantum fluctuations of
various wavelengths
in here
which are the remnants of the quantum
mechanical
processes which took place i will not
try to explain them tonight but let me
just say that after this inflation took
place no matter how long it takes place
it never really gets completely settled
down to complete uniformity
why
quantum mechanics quantum mechanics and
quantum field theory ensure that there
is always
fluctuations
it's kind of an uncertainty principle
thing again
but the the
the fluctuations were there even after
it may have expanded by 10 to the 10 to
the 10 to the 10 to the 10 factor there
were fluctuations
in other words the field was not
completely homogeneous it varied
from place to place by an amount which
was controlled by quantum mechanics if
there was no quantum mechanics it would
be completely flat
with quantum mechanics it varies from
place to place
okay
now let's come to the central picture
which is really what has gotten
the whole subject very exciting over the
last 10 years
let me draw well okay
here's the edge of the cliff
let's draw that edge of the cliff over
here here's the edge of the cliff what
i'm plotting here
vertically
is ordinary space ordinary space x
when i'm plotting horizontally what am i
what am i plotting horizontally
um
i guess
what am i plotting horizontally
uh
a field phi
what i want to draw is the contours the
contours of the field
the contours mean
the surfaces of constant feel like a
contour map
it's not a contour map of elevation it's
a contour map of the field phi
now if i was completely homogeneous
it does vary with time
here's what you would see at one time
you would see a completely homogeneous
field that would mean
that phi is the same
at every point of space here's space
vertically
here's the field phi is horizontal
phi is the same over here as it is over
here as it is over here as it is over
here
that means that phi has gotten very
homogeneous
what would happen with time as time
transpired
as time went on let's transpire
you would roll down the hill
which would mean
that the field would gradually
move
moving to the right
until
it got to the edge over here
when it got to the edge
that's the value of phi where reheating
occurs
it would suddenly fall down
and the
sudden
change in phi would fall down to here so
with time
if you plotted phi
as a function of position
it would be constant
constant a little later constant a
little bit later slowly drifting to the
right
and then
if it were all that homogeneous in other
words all that smooth
every place in space would go over the
edge at the same time
if it were completely homogeneous but
now let's put quantum mechanics in what
does quantum mechanics do it puts some
fluctuation into the field
and so
we could expect that the
that the contours will show some
fluctuation
they will not be exactly homogeneous
and as we roll down the hill
some points reach the edge before the
other before other points
all right here's the way i like to think
about it a bunch of imagine a bunch of
uh soldiers walking in lock step
arm and arm
and they're walking towards the edge of
the cliff
all together
if they are really very well lined up
with no fluctuation in the rank in the
in their
location then they all fall over
simultaneously but what happens if some
soldiers are slightly behind other
soldiers some of them are a little bit
in front some of them are a little bit
slow and they're moving really really
slowly
then there can be a long time delay
between the time one fellow falls over
and the time another fella falls over
so there can be large gaps in the time
between the time that the different
pieces fall over the edge
now
when you fall over the edge when a piece
of space
falls over the edge let's just take a
very simple situation
imagine the field is homogeneous except
for a little bump
so the contour looks like that
it gradually drifts to the right
and this point over here falls off the
edge before this point
so a region of space
is
is created which has been reheated
it's down at the bottom here whereas the
rest of space is still up at the top of
the cliff
all the soldiers except for one uh four
are up on the top
one guy has fallen over
now that one guy has fallen over
that one region of space here
is inflating less rapidly than the
region up here
the vacuum energy down here is small
so it's inflating slowly down here and
rapidly up here what happens
what happens
is the energy that's in here
the new energy that's in there
the new energy that's in there the
kinetic energy the energy of falling off
the cliff here
is expanding less rapidly in space
than the rest of this region out here
so a little lump of energy forms a
little lump of energy forms
a little bit later
let's say a little bit later another
bump goes over the edge
by the time this bump has gone over the
edge
this one has been over for a while and
it has expanded somewhat
it has expanded somewhat then the next
one falls over the edge
what does this lead to this leads to
inhomogeneities
in the energy density over here it leads
to inhomogeneities and the energy
density because
different regions
went over the edge at different times
and their kinetic energies were expanded
and diluted differently
there's a particular pattern
to the kind of fluctuations in energy
that take place but what do these
fluctuations of energy become eventually
these are the seeds of galaxies
the energy density is not uniform after
you fall off the cliff and in fact the
slower that you're moving
the bigger will be the inhomogeneities
if you're moving very very slowly then
the time between
this fellow falling over the edge and
this fellow falling over the edge can be
very large
during that time
this
region may have grown
and then when the next one goes over
this one will have already spread out
so the energy density will be
most the energy density will be most
variable in space if the field is moving
very slowly
would be the other way because the
expansion slows down so we you go over
you'd expand less
oh it has kinetic energy yeah it expands
less yeah
and so that the first
yeah yeah yeah i don't know that's right
that's right that's right so yeah
but
right but the point is that it will
create
it will create variations in the energy
density
that will first of all come from the
original variations in the field but
then magnified by this effect
that
one guy goes over before the next guy
and therefore the effect is different
rates of expansion in the two regions
and that has the effect of making a
variable energy density
that variable energy density
is necessary it's necessary because
without it there would be no galaxies so
it's a funny combination of inflation
inflating the universe and making it
very smooth
but leaving over these little
fluctuations which eventually became the
seeds of galaxies now this is a highly
quantitative story
i'm describing it descriptively
but it's something that can be
quantitatively computed from the quantum
fluctuations in a field and in expanding
space
and you can compare it with the
properties of
of the fluctuations
which you can trace back from known
galaxies
from known properties of the
distribution of galaxies
you can trace it back to the earliest
times right after this reheating took
place
and
it fits it fits well yeah
could you say that it was
cooling
and that after it falls it cool it
doesn't cool as fast
um
no not that's not really quite right
it's a question of expansion
that
that by the time this guy falls over
this guy is already spread out
and done some expansion
no it's not expanding as fast that's
right so it's a combination there's a
competition of things going on
expansion in the in this piece that fell
over the edge
and the inflation of this other
fluctuation here
and it gives rise to a pattern of
fluctuations of energy density
that was
for all practical points of
all practical
purposes
the observational start of the universe
very homogeneous
the later fluctuations are
hotter or
well they're cooler
they're cooler because they've been
stretched
somewhat
when this one
the earlier ones are
hotter than the leaders no the earlier
ones have cooled some
the next one that goes over
you see
when you go over the edge if a little
piece of space goes over the edge it
gets this much energy
all right that much
then that energy is diluted by expansion
afterwards
so if a little piece of space let's say
that much space goes over the edge
it picks up
yeah it's always hotter right
all right so then this one cools a bit
and then the next one falls over it's
somewhat harder
so the heat
so the the hottest places are the
last places to go over the edge yeah so
but
that's right but the main point is that
it leads to
inhomogeneities in the energy density
and those in homogeneities they're small
in fact they were i mean
observationally
the variations in the energy density are
one part and a hundred thousand
variations right no this is this is
primordial density fluctuations
this is neither dark
dark energy is this
that's the energy today
the feet you're saying includes matter
and radiation
yeah that's right it turns into all
kinds of very hot stuff
right matter radiation
and that kind of stuff
and it varies from place to place
observationally about one part and ten
to the five
now that one part and ten to the five is
not a number that we can derive from
this picture that one part and ten to
the five
tells us some constraints on the
shallowness of this
how flat it is the flatness of it the
height of it it puts some constraints on
the parameters
once those constraints are imposed then
it creates a spectrum of fluctuations at
different wavelengths different size
scales
these guys get spread out this guy comes
next he's smaller
in space and so forth
so the effect is that that you have a
fluctuation density spectrum
fluctuations on different scales
what happens
to a variation in energy density that
you start out with
well if you have a bit of over density
over here let's say over density and a
bit of under density over here
the over density
gravitationally attracts material from
the under dense region and so the over
dense region gets more over dense the
under dense region gets
more under dense
and the effect is to magnify
the the spectrum of fluctuations
so just a very very small little
fluctuation to begin with
will gradually build up
depleting the under dense regions
and increasing the overdense regions
and that's the origin of galaxies
so from the spectrum of galaxies from
the spectrum of the spectrum from the
distribution
of galaxies in space one can try to
reconstruct
the density fluctuations that were there
at the very beginning now the very
beginning means after reheating
and compare them
with the theory
that this picture leads to which is
namely quantum fluctuations in the field
being magnified by falling off the edge
and then being processed by gravity
the answer is it fits very well
if it's very well uh
with this picture
and it's the only thing that fits very
well with this picture so you have to
assume that it's a fairly small volume
at that point where
that the observable universe is a small
volume
at which point
galaxy formation
for the time of galaxy formation the
observable universe was
some pretty good fraction of what it is
today
i'm not sure what you're asking me well
i'm just wondering how fast this
movement from under-densed over-deaths
takes place oh well once it starts it
happens fast is that during reheating
no that's after reheating
no that's after at the end of reh at the
time of reheating that's when these
fluctuations were first established
in other words
after going over this edge here
there were some density fluctuations
which were bigger than they were in here
but
whatever they were
but still one part and ten to the five
roughly
one part and a hundred thousand
yeah it magnifies by going over the edge
you magnify the quantum fluctuations but
then gravity still hasn't done its work
gravity doing its work
magnifies them more
and eventually magnifies them a great
deal and turns them into galaxies and
stars and planets and so forth
does that violate the second law it
sounds like it
sounds like entropy is going the wrong
way
it's not um gravity sometimes does
things like that has that effect it
tends to concentrate things yeah but
it's not no it's not violating the
second law nothing can violate the
second law but it does it looks somewhat
counterintuitive
and that
gravity is rather peculiar from the
point of statistical mechanics most
things tend to make things
flat and evenly distributed gravity
tends to make things clump
all right and the clumping actually
increases the entropy
the ultimate is to clump them into black
holes and black holes really have a huge
amount of entropy yeah so uh yeah
how is the microwave background
reflected in all of this the lumps of
the microwave background
uh the lumps in the mic these yeah these
are the lumps in the microwave
background so mostly the mask doesn't
really count that much it's the
microwave background that predominates
here well no it's it's that this stuff
gets imprinted on the microwave
background
so
um
all of this structure
all of the structure
evolved for a period of time gravity did
not become important until after the
surface of last scattering gravity only
became important
after
uh the universe cooled down to below the
temperature of the surface of the sun
so until
that time
the fluctuations were pretty much
primordial
right just these primordial fluctuations
and they imprinted themselves on the
surface of less scattering
so that what we see in the sky in the
surface of less scattering is pretty
much these primordial densities those
regions have to be far enough apart that
the thermal doesn't wash them out
before the surface of last gallery yes
that's right
uh you said that fee was a scalar field
so that wouldn't be an electromagnetic
field no it's not it's not an
electromagnetic field
so how did all this so
the photons just went no what happened
is all of this energy look
what happens to that energy when that
thing hits the floor there some of it
gets converted into electromagnetic
energy not very much incidentally most
of it just gets converted into heat but
the question is what happened when this
field fell down here
okay
it got what could it get turned into
what can that energy get turned into by
the time you settle down at the bottom
what could that energy be
the only thing it could be is particles
of different type
that's the only other thing that we know
that can carry energy is particles of
different type
so in falling off the edge here this
field energy here
presumably got converted into various
kinds of particles
those particles may have been unstable
particles they may have decayed what did
they decay into they decayed into
electrons and positrons protons and
antiprotons or quarks and antiquarks
some photons
and when a large amount of energy is
deposited like that what does it do it
heats turns into heat
after a while it just turns into heat
that heat
eventually became the
photons electrons positrons protons
antiprotons
that uh
so the uh
the reheating
is actually where you get the
manifestation of the uh is where you get
watch
you're getting inflation of the universe
yeah and but it's at that reheating
point where it manifests as a inflation
in the mass and the part well it's where
it becomes particles
it's where that energy gets converted
into radiation particles uh
electrons protons
the the details of this are not known
the details of how you got from here to
electrons positrons and so forth is are
not detailed known the only thing you
know
is that when you have energy contained
and are slowly expanding and
incidentally once you got down here the
universe was much more slowly expanding
on the scale of the rapid particle
reactions that take place the universe
was very slowly expanding when you got
down to here
all right so what happens if you take a
bunch of energy and put it into a pot
which is very very slowly expanding well
it comes to thermal equilibrium it
somehow eventually equilibrates
and
turns into a thermal equilibrium
whatever
whatever the temperature happens to be
so the details of what go on as you go
across here
don't really matter much all you know is
a lot of energy was dumped into a pot
which very very slowly expanded
and that's enough to tell you that some
percentage of it is going to be electron
some of it's going to be positrons some
of it's going to be whatever it is
let me ask this how much of physical
theory survives going back behind the
medium pretty much gravitation
and quantum field theory but none of the
other physical ingredients exist mean up
on the top here yeah
right
that's pretty much right no photons no
particles of mass
and no particles at all right because
the fee has well the only thing that was
there were these fluctuations these
quantum fluctuations in the fields
in particular the quantum fluctuation in
this field phi
and uh
it's not worth calling them particles
so the actual act of the reheating is
that the the cause of the big bang or
yeah that's you um
yeah you may if you like think of the
reheating as the big bang
but it's still it still expanded many
times over before it became the visible
big bang
remember it was so hot when it went over
the edge here
energies here much much higher than
electron positron energies and so forth
much much hotter than the surface of the
sun when it went over here so the
universe was still very
opaque it had to cool down
before it became transparent
so when we look out and see the surface
of last scattering that's very late on
this scale
it's down at the bottom
yeah down to the bottom everything in
everything that we can
measure see observe
happens at the bottom
so by that stretch then when you have
the quantum fluctuations then there are
really multiple
big big bangs right each one as it falls
off is causing well yeah yeah yeah but
well if you like
but on the other hand these fluctuations
are on scales
anywheres from very very much bigger
than the horizon to anywhere is much
much smaller
so some of these fluctuations
were small enough in size
that we see them manifested as
galaxies and stars
even planets
that's probably a stretch galaxies
galaxies and stars
yeah when there's some discussion of
acoustic waves and all this process
doing some
kind of
stuff itself yeah um
right
i guess it has to do with the under
density over density
well this happened the the acoustic
waves are a phenomena that preceded the
uh the gravitational uh
things yeah we should we're going to
talk about acoustic i don't know i'll
just
we have one more class i don't know
all right the acoustic waves are
particularly interesting because they
give us a measuring rod on the sky
all right they give us the measuring rod
which when we look out to the surface of
last scattering
i will tell you about the acoustic waves
the next time
uh
you see
lumps of stuff which were
associated with acoustic waves whose
size you know where do you know them
from that i'll tell you next time
but because you know their size and
because you know their distance you can
start looking at triangles
as those acoustic waves
which are
manifestations of uh
of the processing of these fluctuations
they started to slosh they basically
started to slosh
and they created lumps and the lumps are
of known size because the laws of uh the
acoustics and so forth are known
we know the size of them we know the
distance and we can measure this angle
that's enough to use some geometry to
tell us that space was either flat
positively curved or negatively curved
and uh so those acoustic waves are
important and i
just it's too late for them now
okay
all right do we do we have another class
i've lost track
we have one more two more
two more two more okay good good good
good all right
so the next time i will tell you a
little bit about how the geometry of
space got measured from all of this